all right answer key class two ready
here we go
that's Karma
good karma which is called merit in the
homework okay does it necessarily lead
to Nirvana and Buddhahood
that's all good karma lead to Nirvana
and Buddhahood no okay
why there's thirty good karma okay
there's the Karma you do with bad
motivation okay there's a huge question
in chandrakirti there's a huge question
in chandrakirti ready so according to
DCI at level four level five the way to
get a partner wife or husband is to help
lonely people plant seeds by going to
nursing home find an old lady and old
men and help them and I have had one for
20 years okay
why guess now you already have a partner
I want to keep them you can't stop it's
a pyramid scheme mmm yeah okay
you can't stop okay to keep the partner
going you got to keep listening the old
lady okay so now there comes a big
question in chandi kitty if you go to
visit the old lady and you don't love
her
you just use her as your karmic object
you know you try to find the worst one I
had a guy in Detroit
he raised his hand he said Gessler I
found my old lady I said yeah that's
nice he said no no I found the old lady
I said what do you mean he says she's
poor she's sick and she's broke yeah
poor broken lonely so I can get a
partner money and good health from one
lady he was so happy and it's true okay
I'm sorry so anyway the question comes
in chandrakirti if you visit the old
lady with a cold heart
you just want a boyfriend you don't care
if she dies tomorrow okay will you get
the boyfriend or not you will okay you
will yeah but he'll be a selfish son of
a gun okay you're collecting - Karma's
white and black okay you you will get a
boyfriend but he will be unpleasant it
is good karma but it may not lead you to
Nirvana or Buddhahood if you don't have
the motivation there's such a thing as
dirty good karma okay
good karma that has comes with the you
get the boyfriend but he's selfish
okay or it doesn't have a job and
expects you to make all the money
something like that you know this kind
alright alright next question in the
book the three principal paths you
should understand something important
there's a tradition in the tongue copper
lineage that you cannot give the secret
teachings to a person without a review
of the long Maryam first even if they
pass the eighteen courses it doesn't
matter you you must review the long room
with them before they get the secret
teachings you're not allowed to give the
secret teachings without doing alarm
room again which is a summary of the
Geshe course
so in our diamond way course we made it
the first three courses the first three
courses are actually not diamond way
there are there a review of the long
room and a very famous alarm called the
path to bliss by the first pension Lama
extraordinary poet extraordinary
philosopher extraordin believable okay
so and that's the last time geisha
Luther came here and during those
teachings he shared a lot of experiences
that he had with my teacher okay that's
what I think that's the last time is
here that was 16 years ago okay
cool all right now so one of the big
secret teachings is called Maha mudra
see Maha mudra Maha mudra
in Tibetan Chuck you're Timbo
okay mudra means the seal that a king
puts on his letter when he says forty
thousand cavalry soldiers should march
to Afghanistan and take it over you know
it's the old confirmation email and and
if you were caught with a seal
resembling the Kings seal you would be
killed immediately you see it it means
it's his way of signing a paper okay and
you should never a king would never be
without his seal I like to say the
American president has a black box we
call it the black box and there's a
military high military officer is always
within 20 meters of the American
president that box has the key to send a
nuclear missiles around the world
because right now you have only 15
minutes to define you have 15 minutes to
send them or not to send them so they're
just they stand outside his bedroom all
night once you become president I saw
when Obama came out of the White House
he was like huh you know come you got
the box I don't have the box anymore you
know he was so happy you know why am I
talking about that it's like the muder
okay the king the emperor must have
there nobody can touch it they must have
it with them
okay so it became a word to describe the
direct perception emptiness okay
especially the emptiness of your mind
okay it became a word that means the
direct perception emptiness and then in
Tantra in the secret teachings it became
a word for your spiritual partner
okay mudra in the secret teachings means
your spiritual partner okay and that's
the fastest way to practice the diamond
way if you can find a highly qualified
spiritual partner practiced together
with them that's the fastest way to do
the fastest way okay
it's the highest way and there are
stories in the monastery about pub uncle
spiritual partner very interesting he
had a special cave and there's all these
stories about this angel who used to
walk out of the cave like people just
run into her you know and their work wow
you know Buddha had a spiritual partner
called Tilottama okay and according to
the diamond way he only became
enlightened because he had a spiritual
partner and they became enlightened on
the same morning together so imagine
you're sitting together with your
partner the Sun comes up at Diamond
Mountain and with the first rays of
light you both get enlightened that's
the real story okay and you can read it
in the text John recovered those Turks
it's highly secret books of Gumi I asked
for those books because my teacher
became the oven so I said you're Abbot
right he said yeah I said give me those
books I want to input them he said no
and we have an input Center about a
hundred yards from the monastery in
Hunter so I gave up I couldn't get those
books and twelve highly secret books
then one day from Hunter which is all
ladies the data came all of it all
twelve books you know I'm like
I call him how'd you get these books
they're like we know some of the mugs
I'm like man good job you know they
didn't do anything bad okay they just
you know asked for them and so the whole
story of telethon is in those books and
I translated it and it's in course
seventeen okay of the diamond way okay
so copper had a partner tongue Shama the
lady with the red hat and that's a
beautiful story which you can read he
was assigned a partner by manjushri okay
and he didn't really want one and that's
another story
okay but my jury said look you've gone
too slow you need a partner that's a
beautiful story okay you can kind of
read that in that big red book if you
look carefully we even made a painting
of her okay alright anyway why are we
talking about Tantra in the middle of
course one class one of the non Tantra
why are we talking about my Munna
yeah beautiful you cannot touch the
secret teachings without these three
attitudes you will fail you will fail
okay something bad will happen something
really bad will happen
we had people die here okay something
bad will happen okay if you try to
practice the secret teachings without
those three attitudes if your motivation
is not I'm tired I got a bit got a gun
gotta be a Buddha
I gotta see emptiness directly if you
don't have those three in your heart you
will fail in the second eighteen courses
you will fail spectacularly like
amazingly it'll be a real amazing okay
so it's actually these three are
protecting you for when you get to the
higher teachings okay if you don't have
them you cannot practice those teachings
okay so a bunker and betrayed tsongkhapa
they're trying to sell you first grade
lung room you know and they're telling
you if you don't learn addition you
can't learn calculus you know see
calculate it got it you need this stuff
if you want to become a Buddha you've
got to have the three principal pass if
you want to practice my mudra Tantra
with the partner by the way why is a
partner called mudra you can never lead
them you say I mean it's like the
emperor stem okay
you can't and once you make that
relationship you should stay with them
okay and until you're enlightened it
doesn't mean you can't switch partners
if it happens okay but it does mean when
you make that commitment to use that
path you must have a partner okay you
can't let go of that you can't give up
on that idea okay if you lose your
partner you should find a new one a good
one okay
but you can't give up okay like you can
have fights with your partner you can
separate for your partner but you must
find your partner okay you can't give up
its mudra got it okay
and if you don't have the three
principal paths you will lose your
partner and bad stuff will happen got it
okay all right
yeah so that's homework not a question
number 20 what's the relationship
between the three principal paths and
the Great Seal and the word principal is
misspelled in the homework well it
happens to the best of us okay question
4 what are the two principal causes of
being a Buddha and we call it your any
methods same method and wisdom ok method
and wisdom they're called the two wings
of the bird if you don't have two wings
you can't fly okay here's method here's
wisdom okay
method is Bodhisattvas training training
as a bodhisattva
basically wisdom is the understanding
emptiness okay if you don't have these
two you can't fly you'll never make it
okay method so method is a code word for
the activities and thinking of a
bodhisattva wisdom is wisdom okay
hundred dollars when's the last time you
thought about these things if you get it
wrong you owe me $100 nice
dang he's the same expensive dude $100
yeah get wha do you oh good so don't you
okay got it
collection of Marin and with them okay
method and with them gone in okay we'll
talk about it where does that come from
for zero dollars the 60 versus of it's
the last of the 60 verses that Nick is
translating okay that prayer you do
every night all right okay here we go
question five what's the main elements
of method and what's the main what's
inside a method and what's inside of
wisdom I'll give you a clue split the
three principal paths into those two
which is which where does renunciation
belong with methane
where does bodhichitta belong math where
it is wisdom belong with mr. yay okay
you pass questions fire Nick I'm sorry
Tim I'm on schedule okay now there's a
special teaching called the bodies of a
Buddha there's a special teaching called
the bodies of a Buddha kaya right
dharmakaya nirmanakaya sambhogakaya kiya
kiya swab of wakaya okay there's lots of
caius bodies of the buddha okay and it's
a very very important teaching in
Buddhism is the different bodies of a
Buddha okay and I'm sorry you know it's
on the way here I was thinking how do I
explain bodies they're not bodies
they're not separate bodies okay it
doesn't mean that it just means part
okay Buddha has two parts
or Buddha has three parts or Buddha has
four parts okay so there's three
different ways to teach the caius you
can teach two
you can teach three you can teach four
okay I'm gonna do two with you to start
with okay ready and it's on your
homework number one say so cool
real pacaya what does it mean yeah the
physical part of a Buddha the physical
part of a Buddha okay the part you can
see touch okay that's called a rubric
ayah you want to go deeper two parts
that there's two bodies inside the
physical body what give me any of them
give me one yeah those two one is called
emanation body the one you send to
planets okay that the copy of you that
you sent to other planets you can be a
dog making an old lady happy in Los
Angeles and you can be an uber driver in
Beijing lifts dick do doo deee deee
sorry you can be a didi driver in
Beijing at the same time okay if it
makes people happy and that's called
emanation bunny you have the power to
split your body and serve multiple
people at the same time got it easy
right what's some pogo kaya
that's called enjoyment buddy it just
means your head quarter body head
quarter physical body in Buddha paradise
okay headquarter physical body it has
done how many signs 112 I taught it here
for like a week but that was a while ago
and we got leaky teacups 32 major signs
80 secondary science on the Buddhist
body that body coke classic classic body
that's the Samba with her that's the one
that stays in heaven okay
then they come here they look like say
gee they look like Steven they look like
Connie
okay that's near Monica got it
okay now the other body when you teach
it
two bodies is called dharmakaya said
dharmakaya okay cool
it also you want to go deeper it also
has two parts which is why you can make
four bodies out of two bodies okay
it also has two parts number one the
easy one is the mental state of a Buddha
is jnana dharmakaya okay there's jnana
brahmacari the omniscience of a Buddha
the ability to see all things at all
times
okay past present and future that
ability is a separate body body number
three so far tonight right what was
number one mnemonic I send yourself as a
dog to LA send yourself as a daily
driver to Beijing and what's the stuck
away yeah homebody
you know paradise bunny I sometimes I
like to call it paradise bunny okay with
the 112 Mars okay body number three it's
mental the mental state of a Buddha can
see all things at all times now body
number four is the most interesting one
what's it called the emptiness body says
wah wah wah wah wah wah sanskrit doesn't
really have a v swore bah bah wah wah
wah
okay swab of our kiya okay emptiness
body for $100 and not word UK you're not
if you want to answer this one dollar
tell me what's super cool about the swab
of a car the emptiness body
yeah you have it now you already have it
it's your Buddha nature it's the what's
the Sanskrit word word for $10 Buddha
nature in Sanskrit huh well the target
the garbha say to target the garbha okay
Garba means the womb of a woman the
target a means Buddha and and you
already have this moon every person has
you have body number four you already
have body number four okay you want to
impress your friends at a cocktail party
I saw a nice cartoon in The New Yorker
there's this nerdy guy talking to this
lady in a miniskirt and she's there at a
cocktail party and then the guys are
trying to impress the girl right so and
they and in the cartoon she says no I
don't want to know your secret mantra
he's just trying to okay anyway why did
I talk about that
[Music]
how's that connector cocktail party
oh yeah you want to impress your friends
okay if you meet a girl at a cocktail
party you can say do you know that party
is already enlightened you know you got
25% Buddha in you already and then she
said oh wow I'm so impressed do you want
to go out with me
I told Veronica you know I'm a real
Tibetan grammar nerd I'm the only one
she said oh okay anyway you're already
25% Bruner okay
it means you already have emptiness
which means you can change into a Buddha
okay the the chew-toy can become a pimp
got it if the stick didn't have
emptiness the to toy couldn't become a
pen got it so you're right now we're all
two toys and you can become a pen you
can't become a Buddha why because you're
not anything from your own sign
if you plant the seeds this can change
okay got it
so that's your blessed fourth buddy okay
why are we talking about that homework
question number seven what are the
causes of the two bodies
yeah merit and wisdom you say it every
night right what's the body that's
created by wisdom dharmakaya Dharma body
which just means the mind and the
emptiness of a Buddha together because
one is looking at the other got it okay
the mind of a buna and the emptiness the
Buddha together are called dharmakaya
the the body of all things okay and then
what's the cause of the physical body of
a Buddha good good karma good deeds okay
Sonam now auntie no uncle you're hoping
I'm finishing the class but I'm not
they won the atomic Unni Tom bikini top
Ashok may all beings achieve the two
holy bodies okay that's what we're
talking about okay got it
alright Oh Tim we're gonna make it I
think which one of the three principal
paths causes each of the bodies which
principal path causes the physical body
of a Buddha huh second one for sure and
also the first one okay getting tired of
this life getting tired of seeing people
die around you and the wish for
enlightenment are our causes for the
physical body mainly that's what you're
saying that the background when you want
to fudge something mainly okay and then
what's the cost for the wisdom body the
direct perception emptiness mainly okay
got it
I'd like to tell you something cool that
happened to me okay I had this stuff
going on all day with Ken Rinpoche I was
so lucky to live with him
so everything we talked about with
Dharma and so I would ask him questions
constantly and he would try to avoid me
but I I learned to make Momo's so he
couldn't avoid me which is the most
delicious Tibetan food and in fact I'm
gonna make some next week forget it all
right
I bought the pot and new pot special one
okay for him anyway
I said Rinpoche what's the connection
between renunciation and bodhichitta
what do you think he said
good yeah okay understand bodhichitta is
just renunciation spread towards
everybody got it it's such a cool answer
okay
the second principle path is just the
first principle path aimed at everybody
I've got it
the first principle path is named at me
I'm tired I'm tired of seeing friends
die I'm tired of being in this kind of
world okay then when you feel like that
for everybody you reached Path number
two it's principal partner got it cool
cool man
figure cool good job bang okay
what's that thing if a monkey hits on a
typewriter all day one word will come
out
that's my Chinese okay what are the two
obstacles to Buddhahood yeah one is
called mental affliction obstacles okay
mental affliction obstacles the second
one is called obstacles to omniscience
okay somebody other than word tell me
why the wording is confusing for $100
somebody who's not word tell me why
these two words are a little confusing
now I mean it's a good guess but and
it's true but it's not what I want
I can tell it's coming
good yeah think about it
yeah good think about it in Tibetan the
first obstacle is called glacier
obstacle but it doesn't mean obstacle to
reaching glaciers
it means the obstacle which is collision
you see that mean but the traditional
second obstacle is the obstacle to
omniscience then it's an obstacle to the
goal it's not the obstacle so they're
not the same okay got it and it's an
easier way to remember it I'll say it
again okay
the first kind of obstacle which is an
obstacle to Nirvana is all of your
clashes the clashes equal the obstacle
got it the clashes are the problem got
it the name of the second obstacle is
omniscience obstacle and that doesn't
equal anymore
it means gonna stop you from omniscience
you understand it the wording is weird
okay if you don't understand ask
somebody else okay haha question 10 yay
I'm on the last one I did it so that
means I can do some teacher training
stuff tonight okay or at least I can
start okay why was jetsam Kapur able to
write 10,000 pages of incredibly deep
and difficult explanation of Buddhism he
cheated yeah he learned how to talk to
manjushri okay
in English we call it plagiarism it's
where you write your book and you steal
everything from DCI or somebody like
that okay he stole everything from
manjushri and he looked really smart it
looks like some coppers really smart but
he got it off from Manju she in fact so
well that later he was accused of being
Manju okay
like he report to all his friends their
friends are like how do you write this
thing he's like I had help from
manjushri and then later his close
disciples he said
she got it he's really close to Manju
she got it okay now you have finished
homework too